Preliminary Guide to the Joseph John Spengler Papers, [ca. 1896]-1987
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joseph John Spengler papers [ca. 1896]-1987
Spengler, Joseph John, 1902-
111.8 linear feet Extent: 60,387 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.01242
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However some of the materials are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
In addition, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Joseph John Spengler Papers was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1987-2000.
Biographical Note
Professor of economics at Duke University, 1934-1979. Spengler married Dorothy "Dot" Kress in 1927. He died in 1991.
Collection Overview
Chiefly correspondence, printed material, critiques of publications, bibliographies, class notes, and other papers relating to his career, publications, and affiliation with different economics associations (26,378 items, 52.7 linear feet; dated 1928-1987). Some are photocopies of Spengler's correspondence with William Richard Allen. The collection also includes manuscripts of some of his works, information concerning Duke University's administrative policies and staff, reprints of published articles relating to his career, and a charcoal portrait. (1-9-87, 88-010, 93-180, 00-213) No container lists exist for these accessions.
Addition #93-294 (34,009 items, 59.1 linear feet; dated [ca. 1896]-[ca. 1976], bulk 1914-1960) contains primarily business and Spengler and Kress family correspondence, especially between Dot and Joe ([ca. 1919]-[ca. 1976]). Also includes manuscripts for Dot's genealogical novel, Family Saga in America ([ca. 1930s]) and Joe's work, Life in America; as well as Dot's journals and diaries (1924-1939, 1969). There are Christmas cards, postcards, and newspaper clippings; photographs of family and friends, including 2 tintypes, 32 cartes-de-visite, 1 color and 91 black-and-white prints, and 76 healthy nitrate negatives; and lace knitted by Dot's grandmother.
Also includes 6 photograph albums kept by Dot, two of which contain pictures taken by her with a brownie camera in and of Piqua, OH (1914-1919). The other albums contain photographs and memorabilia depicting Dot's life as a college student at Miami University, OH (1919-1921); and two showing views of the Spengler's homes, friends, and life in Tuscon, AZ, Tampa, FL (1930-1938), and Durham, NC and Duke University (1932-1940). The latter also records the 1938 Duke University faculty baseball team.
Subject Headings
Allen, William Richard, 1924-; Spengler, Dorothy; Spengler, Joseph John, 1902-; Spengler family; Kress family; Duke University. Dept. of Economics; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University -- Pictorial works; Miami University (Oxford, Ohio); Economics -- Study and teaching; Durham (N.C.) -- Pictorial works; Tucson (Ariz.) -- Pictorial works; Tampa (Fla.) -- Pictorial works; Piqua (Ohio) -- Pictorial works; Black-and-white photographs; Color photograph; Nitrate negatives; Photograph albums; Tintypes; Cartes-de-visite; Clippings; Lace; Diaries
Contents of Collection
- Accession 1993-294
  - Contents of Box 1: (Box 1)
    - Business Correspondence, 1938-1941 (Box 1)
  - Contents of Box 2: (Box 2)
    - Business Correspondence, 1941-1942, undated (Box 2)
    - Labeled folders (Box 2)
      - Economic Fallacies (Box 2)
      - Text Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Contents of Box 3: (Box 3)
    - Foldered materials (Box 3)
      - Business Correspondence, 1943-1945 (Box 3)
      - Articles (Box 3)
      - [unlabeled] (Box 3)
  - Contents of Box 4: (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1930s and 1940s, undated (Box 4)
      - Personal and Business (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - [loose papers] (Box 4)
  - Contents of Box 5: (Box 5)
    - Business Correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box 5)
    - South Africa Trip, 1968 July (Box 5)
  - Contents of Box 6: (Box 6)
    - Correspondence (Box 6)
      - Personal Interest (Box 6)
      - Important Pre-1940 (Box 6)
    - Daily Reminder Book (Box 6)
    - [loose papers] (Box 6)
  - Contents of Box 7: (Box 7)
    - Manuscript of book by Dot Spengler, Family Saga in America, 1939 (Box 7)
  - Contents of Box 8: (Box 8)
    - Correspondence in Journal, 1939-1940 (Box 8)
    - Family Saga in America (Box 8)
  - Contents of Box 9: (Box 9)
    - Family Saga in America, rewrites and copies (Box 9)
  - Contents of Box 10: (Box 10)
    - Family Saga in America, rewrites and copies (Box 10)
  - Contents of Box 11: (Box 11)
    - Family Saga in America, copies (Box 11)
    - Correspondence From Margaret Blomquist to Spenglers, [1970s-1980s] (Box 11)
  - Contents of Box 12: (Box 12)
    - Blomquist Correspondence, continued (Box 12)
    - Life in America, by Joseph Spengler (Box 12)
    - Correspondence from Dot Spengler to Joseph Spengler, 1928 (Box 12)
    - General and Personal Correspondence, 1929 (Box 12)
  - Contents of Box 13: (Box 13)
    - Notebook with newspaper clippings (Box 13)
    - General and Personal Correspondence, 1927-1934 (Box 13)
    - [loose materials] (Box 13)
  - Contents of Box 14: (Box 14)
    - General and Personal Correspondence (Box 14)
    - Correspondence from Dot Spengler to Joseph Spengler, 1928 (Box 14)
    - Short Trip, 1957-1959 (Box 14)
  - Contents of Box 15: (Box 15)
    - Short Trips, continued (Box 15)
  - Contents of Box 16: (Box 16)
    - Correspondence between Dot and Joseph Spengler, 1924-1925 (Box 16)
  - Contents of Box 17: (Box 17)
    - Correspondence between Dot and Joseph Spengler, continued (Box 17)
    - Correspondence from G. Long to Dot Spengler, 1937 (Box 17)
  - Contents of Box 18: (Box 18)
    - Correspondence (Box 18)
      - Between Dot and Joseph Spengler, 1925 and 1942 (Box 18)
      - To Dot Spengler, 1939 (Box 18)
      - To Dot and Joseph Spengler (Box 18)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
    - Tax, bank, and insurance statements (Box 18)
  - Contents of Box 19: (Box 19)
    - Correspondence (Box 19)
      - From Joseph Spengler to Dot Spengler, 1942 (Box 19)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 19)
    - Pictures of Joe's Home (Box 19)
  - Contents of Box 20: (Box 20)
    - Correspondence (Box 20)
      - Between Dot Kress and Joseph Spengler, 1924-1925 (Box 20)
      - To Spenglers, 1938-1939 (Box 20)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 20)
    - Bank Book (Box 20)
  - Contents of Box 21: (Box 21)
    - Correspondence (Box 21)
      - From Joseph Spengler to Dot Kress, 1924 (Box 21)
      - From Dot Kress to Joseph Spengler, 1926 (Box 21)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 21)
  - Contents of Box 22: (Box 22)
    - Correspondence (Box 22)
      - From Dot Kress to Joseph Spengler, 1926 (Box 22)
      - From Joseph Spengler to Dot Kress, 1925 (Box 22)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 22)
  - Contents of Box 23: (Box 23)
    - Correspondence (Box 23)
      - From Joseph Spengler to Dot Kress, 1924-1927 (Box 23)
      - From H. Kress to Dot Spengler, 1930-1933 (Box 23)
      - From Dot Kress to Joseph Spengler, 1925 (Box 23)
      - Personal, [1960s] (Box 23)
  - Contents of Box 24: (Box 24)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1959-1960 and [1960s-1970s] (Box 24)
  - Contents of Box 25: (Box 25)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 25)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 25)
    - Magazine Article on Israel, 1960 (Box 25)
    - Dot's Keepsakes, 1950-1951 (Box 25)
  - Contents of Box 26: (Box 26)
    - Dot's Log and Letters (Box 26)
    - Memos on and of Joe (Box 26)
    - Dot's Keepsakes (Box 26)
    - Funeral Register for Georgia Long, 1946 (Box 26)
  - Contents of Box 27: (Box 27)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 27)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 27)
    - [loose material] (Box 27)
    - Correspondence to and from Joe, 1969 (Box 27)
    - Joe's Official Biography and Bibliography (Box 27)
    - Joe's Correspondence, 1963 (Box 27)
    - To President Knight (Box 27)
  - Contents of Box 28: (Box 28)
    - Business Material (Box 28)
      - [loose material] (Box 28)
      - Correspondence (Box 28)
      - Newspaper Clippings (Box 28)
      - Speeches (Box 28)
  - Contents of Box 29: (Box 29)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 29)
    - Business Material and Correspondence, [1950s-1980s] (Box 29)
  - Contents of Box 30: (Box 30)
    - Labeled folders containing Business related papers, [1960s-1970] (Box 30)
    - [loose material] (Box 30)
  - Contents of Box 31: (Box 31)
    - Diaries of Dot Spengler, 1970-1973 (Box 31)
  - Contents of Box 32: (Box 32)
    - Dot Spengler's Material (Box 32)
      - Birthday book while at Miami University, 1924 (Box 32)
      - Journals, 1930-1931, 1937-1938, and 1938-1939 (Box 32)
      - List of books read with descriptions (Box 32)
      - Address Book (Box 32)
    - Correspondence from Dick Harvill to Spenglers, 1968-1972 (Box 32)
  - Contents of Box 33: (Box 33)
    - Correspondence (Box 33)
      - From Joseph Spengler to Dot Spengler, 1928 (Box 33)
      - From Dick Harvill, 1975-1976 (Box 33)
      - From Dot Kress to Joseph Spengler, 1925 (Box 33)
    - Bills, receipts, and contracts (Box 33)
  - Contents of Box 34: (Box 34)
    - Correspondence (Box 34)
      - Miscellaneous letters to Spenglers (Box 34)
      - Professional (Box 34)
      - From Dot Kress to Joseph Spengler, 1925 (Box 34)
  - Contents of Box 35: (Box 35)
    - Farewell Book from Mary Craig to Joseph Spengler (Box 35)
    - Newspaper clippings and photocopies (Box 35)
    - [loose papers] (Box 35)
    - Pictures of Joseph Spengler (Box 35)
  - Contents of Box 36: (Box 36)
    - Foldered personal and business materials including newspaper clippings and correspondence [1970s-1980s] (Box 36)
  - Contents of Box 37: (Box 37)
    - Foldered materials continued (Box 37)
  - Contents of Box 38: (Box 38)
    - Family Correspondence, 1944-1950 (Box 38)
      Includes clippings as well as correspondence, mainly between Dot and Joseph Spengler.
  - Contents of Box 39: (Box 39)
    - Family Correspondence, continued (Box 39)
    - Foldered business and economic material (Box 39)
  - Contents of Box 40: (Box 40)
    - Foldered business and economic material, continued (Box 40)
    - Personal Correspondence between Dot and Joseph Spengler, 1959-1960 (Box 40)
  - Contents of Box 41: (Box 41)
    - Personal Correspondence, continued, 1940s-1970s (Box 41)
  - Contents of Box 42: (Box 42)
    - Personal Correspondence, continued (Box 42)
  - Contents of Box 43: (Box 43)
    - Personal Correspondence, continued (Box 43)
    - Dot's Diary, 1969 (Box 43)
    - Journal (Box 43)
  - Contents of Box 44: (Box 44)
    - Correspondence between Dot Spengler and Ollie Kress, [Dot's mother], [1960s] (Box 44)
  - Contents of Box 45: (Box 45)
    - Correspondence between Spengler and Kress, continued (Box 45)
  - Contents of Box 46: (Box 46)
    - Correspondence between Spengler and Kress, continued (Box 46)
  - Contents of Box 47: (Box 47)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1972-1976 (Box 47)
  - Contents of Box 48: (Box 48)
    - Personal Correspondence, continued (Box 48)
    - Joe's Recollections of Life (Box 48)
    - Professional and economic papers (Box 48)
    - Manuscripts and magazines belonging to Dot Spengler, early [1900s] (Box 48)
    - Photographs of the Spenglers taken at various times (Box 48)
  - Contents of Box 49: (Box 49)
    - Manuscripts and magazines, continued (Box 49)
    - Correspondence between Dot Spengler and Ollie Kress, 1968-1972 (Box 49)
  - Contents of Box 50: (Box 50)
    - Correspondence between Spengler and Kress, continued (Box 50)
    - Dot's Christmas Cards, [1950s-1970s] (Box 50)
  - Contents of Box 51: (Box 51)
    - Dot's Christmas Cards, continued (Box 51)
    - Correspondence concerning Carol Kress Spence, [1950s-1970s] (Box 51)
  - Contents of Box 52: (Box 52)
    - Spence correspondence, continued (Box 52)
  - Contents of Box 53: (Box 53)
    - Spence correspondence, continued (Box 53)
  - Contents of Box 54: (Box 54)
    - Spence correspondence, continued (Box 54)
  - Contents of Box 55: (Box 55)
    - Life in America by Joseph Spengler (Box 55)
    - Labeled folders (Box 55)
    - Diary entries by Dot Spengler, 1924-1927 (Box 55)
  - Contents of Box 56: (Box 56)
    - Dot's Manuscript (Box 56)
    - Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 56)
  - Contents of Box 57: (Box 57)
    - Correspondence, continued (Box 57)
    - Western Trip Correspondence, 1919 (Box 57)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 57)
  - Contents of Box 58: (Box 58)
    - Correspondence from Joseph Spengler to Dot Kress, Summer 1927 (Box 58)
    - Receipts, 1923 (Box 58)
    - Journal and date book (Box 58)
    - Miscellaneous material (Box 58)
  - Contents of Box 59: (Box 59)
    - Correspondence from Dot Kress to Joseph Spengler, 1923 (Box 59)
    - Miscellaneous material (Box 59)
    - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 59)
  - Contents of Box 60: (Box 60)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 60)
    - Professional correspondence and articles (Box 60)
    - Family Saga in America Part IV, 1907-1927 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence from Joseph Spengler to Dot Kress, 1923 (Box 60)
    - Pictures of unidentified boy and mother with son and daughter, 1909 (Box 60)
  - Contents of Box 61: (Box 61)
    - Correspondence (Box 61)
      - Kid Letters, 1903-1917 (Box 61)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 61)
  - Contents of Box 62: (Box 62)
    - Correspondence (Box 62)
      - Fall 1921 (Box 62)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 62)
  - Contents of Box 63: (Box 63)
    - Correspondence (Box 63)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 63)
      - Fall 1922 (Box 63)
      - 1936 (Box 63)
  - Contents of Box 64: (Box 64)
    - Correspondence (Box 64)
      - 1938 (Box 64)
      - 1934 (Box 64)
      - 1941-1942 (Box 64)
  - Contents of Box 65: (Box 65)
    - Correspondence (Box 65)
      - Fall 1939 (Box 65)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 65)
      - 1940 (Box 65)
      - Fall 1935-1936 (Box 65)
  - Contents of Box 66: (Box 66)
    - Correspondence (Box 66)
      - 1934 (Box 66)
      - Summer 1935 (Box 66)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 66)
      - 1942 (Box 66)
  - Contents of Box 67: (Box 67)
    - Correspondence (Box 67)
      - 1941 (Box 67)
      - Fall 1940 (Box 67)
      - 1938 (Box 67)
      - Fall/Winter 1935-1936 (Box 67)
      - 1942 (Box 67)
      - 1940-1942 (Box 67)
  - Contents of Box 68: (Box 68)
    - Correspondence (Box 68)
      - 1935 (Box 68)
      - 1938 (Box 68)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 68)
  - Contents of Box 69: (Box 69)
    - Correspondence (Box 69)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 69)
      - 1935-1936 (Box 69)
    - New Version Part I (Box 69)
  - Contents of Box 70: (Box 70)
    - New Version, continued, Parts II, III, and IV (Box 70)
    - Old Version Parts I and II (Box 70)
  - Contents of Box 71: (Box 71)
    - Old Version, continued, Parts I, II, III, and IV (Box 71)
    - Miscellaneous Papers (Box 71)
    - Correspondence from friends, 1935-1936 (Box 71)
  - Contents of Box 72: (Box 72)
    - Correspondence (Box 72)
      - From folks, 1940 (Box 72)
      - From family, 1937 (Box 72)
      - From Mom, 1941 (Box 72)
    - Last Version Parts I, II, III, and IV (Box 72)
    - Dot's Notebook, 1930 (Box 72)
  - Contents of Box 73: (Box 73)
    - Journal and notebook (Box 73)
    - Correspondence, 1920-1921 (Box 73)
  - Contents of Box 74: (Box 74)
    - Correspondence (Box 74)
      - 1920-1921 (Box 74)
      - 1933 (Box 74)
      - 1928 (Box 74)
      - 1929 (Box 74)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 74)
    - Journal and date book (Box 74)
  - Contents of Box 75: (Box 75)
    - Correspondence (Box 75)
      - 1929 (Box 75)
      - 1935-1937 (Box 75)
      - 1925 (Box 75)
      - 1924 (Box 75)
      - 1927 (Box 75)
  - Contents of Box 76: (Box 76)
    - Correspondence (Box 76)
      - 1924-1927 (Box 76)
      - 1924 (Box 76)
      - 1922 (Box 76)
      - 1921-1922 (Box 76)
  - Contents of Box 77: (Box 77)
    - Small journals (Box 77)
    - Correspondence (Box 77)
      - 1925 (Box 77)
      - 1926 (Box 77)
      - 1932-1933 (Box 77)
      - Fall 1924 (Box 77)
  - Contents of Box 78: (Box 78)
    - Correspondence (Box 78)
      - 1925 (Box 78)
      - 1927-1928 (Box 78)
      - 1923 (Box 78)
  - Contents of Box 79: (Box 79)
    - Correspondence (Box 79)
      - 1924 (Box 79)
      - 1927 (Box 79)
  - Contents of Box 80: (Box 80)
    - Correspondence (Box 80)
      - 1924 (Box 80)
      - Fall 1928 (Box 80)
      - 1926 (Box 80)
    - Miscellaneous papers, [ca. 1933] (Box 80)
  - Contents of Box 81: (Box 81)
    - Correspondence (Box 81)
      - 1933 (Box 81)
      - 1926 (Box 81)
      - 1928-1929 (Box 81)
      - 1932-1933 (Box 81)
      - 1925 (Box 81)
    - [loose papers] (Box 81)
  - Contents of Box 82: (Box 82)
    - Correspondence (Box 82)
      - From friends, 1935 (Box 82)
      - From family, 1937 (Box 82)
      - From Dot to Folks, 1935 (Box 82)
  - Contents of Box 83: (Box 83)
    - Correspondence (Box 83)
      - [loose] (Box 83)
      - From family, 1938 (Box 83)
      - Joe's Correspondence, 1936-1940 (Box 83)
      - From Joseph Spengler to Kresses, 1933-1934 (Box 83)
  - Contents of Box 84: (Box 84)
    - Correspondence (Box 84)
      - From Dot to Family, 1934-1935 (Box 84)
      - 1937 (Box 84)
      - From friends, 1939 (Box 84)
  - Contents of Legal-size Box 86: (Box 85)
    - Academic and economic papers (Box 85)
  - Contents of box 86: (Box 86)
    - Novel Miscellaney, 1939 (Box 86)
    - Correspondence, 1934-1940 (Box 86)
  - Contents of box 87: (Box 87)
    - Correspondence, friends, family, and business, 1936-1941 (Box 87)
  - Contents of box 88: (Box 88)
    - Correspondence, friends, family, and business, 1936-1940 (Box 88)
    - [Receipts, including for house repair/building] (Box 88)
    - Third Best Copy [of Dot's novel], Part III (Box 88)
  - Contents of box 89: (Box 89)
    - Third Best Copy [of Dot's novel], Part II (Box 89)
    - [From inside box labeled:] Longhand manuscript (Box 89)
    - Dot's Rewrites, Summer 1939 (Box 89)
  - Contents of box 90: (Box 90)
    - Dot's Rewrites, Summer 1939, continued (Box 90)
    - Original copy-Novel Part I (Box 90)
    - 1937 [Novel] Parts I-IV minus revisions and minus [perfect] pages (Box 90)
    - Loose newspapers, postcards, and photographs removed from 1930-1931 photograph album in box 94 (Box 90)
    - Loose photographs removed from 1919-1921 Stunt Book in box 93 (Box 90)
  - Contents of Box 91: (Box 91)
    - Dot's Reunions (Box 91)
    - Photographs of [primarily Kress] family and friends, including black-and-white prints, tintypes, and cartes-de-visite (Box 91)
  - Contents of box 92: (Box 92)
    - Two photograph albums containing prints taken by Dot Kress in Piqua, OH, with her brownie camera, [ca. 1914-1918] (Box 92)
  - Contents of box 93: (Box 93)
    - Stunt Book scrapbook containing photographs and memorabilia created by Dot Kress in college at Miami University, OH, 1919-1921 (Box 93)
  - Contents of box 94: (Box 94)
    - Photograph album reflecting Joe and Dot Spengler's life in Tuscon, AZ, and Tampa, FL, 1930-1931 (Box 94)
  - Contents of box 95: (Box 95)
    - Photograph album showing the construction and development of Joe and Dot's home and garden in Durham, NC, 1939-1941 (Box 95)
  - Contents of box 96: (Box 96)
    - Photograph album depicting Joe and Dot's life in Tuscon, AZ (University of Arizona), Tampa, FL, and Durham, NC (Duke University), 1932-1938 (Box 96)
      Includes photographs of the Duke University faculty baseball team, 1938 and views of the University and Durham, 1938.
    - Photographs and information from Joe's retirement dinner, 1972 (Box 96)
    - Cover of box in which scrapbook and photograph albums were originally stored; contains notes by Dot (Box 96)
  - Contents of box 97: (Box 97)
    - Lace knitted by Grandmother Kress (Box 97)
  - Contents of box 98: (Box 98)
    - 76 healthy nitrate sheet negatives. (Box 98)
Materials Cataloged Separately
The following book was removed from accession #93-294 and cataloged separately:
The Legend of Sleepy Hollow, ills. Arthur I. Keller, 1906.